A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests, Series D FA313
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Democracy
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1940-1949 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    America First Committee, American Youth for Democracy. Miscellaneous plans. Dorothy Thompson's "Ring for Freedom." Appeals for aid and support from patriotic organizations. All declined. Anti-Communist organizations. Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributions to Committee to Strengthen the Frontiers of Freedom in 1960. Appeals for aid to anti-Castro groups. Laurance S. Rockefeller made 1961 contribution to Freedom Fund, Inc. issuing booklets for use by Russian tourists. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    61
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1940-1949 (Box 7, Folder 0035A)
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1949-1959 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1949-1959 (Box 7, Folder 0036A)
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Democracy - Americanism, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 0038A)
  - Democracy - Americanism - American Forum of Democracy, Inc. - J. Matthews, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    A scheme by Matthews to make the people aware of what democracy is. Unsuccessful attempt to get Rockefeller's contribution and participation. Correspondents include C. J. Matthews, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Democracy - Americanism - American Forum of Democracy, Inc. - J. Matthews, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 0039A)
  - Democracy - Council for Democracy, 1940-1949 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    Mobilize and unify the minds of Americans in defense of democracy. Nelson A. Rockefeller interested but not active. Influential group of people. Appeal to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined. Council's activity and budget dwindled after war. John D. Rockefeller 3rd made $500 contribution in 1942. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., R. G. Swing, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    61.1
  - Democracy - Council for Democracy - John D. Rockefeller 3rd - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1941-1950 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    Programs to save America, anti-Red, anti-Nazi. Many shades of political opinion. Rockefeller office consistently shied away from expressing an opinion regarding the several plans promoted. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined request to talk with Madame Chaing Kai Shek. Anti-Communist after end of WW II. No family interest or action. Many representatives of the lunatic fringe. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    61.2
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1941-1950 (Box 8, Folder 0042A)
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1954-1961 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1954-1961 (Box 8, Folder 0043A)
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1951-1959 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Democracy - Subversive Activities, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 0044A)
  - Democracy - Dr. Harold Rugg - A. G. Rudd, 1940-1952 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    Controversy over progressivism in schools. H. Rugg's textbook symbol of leftist tendencies. A. Rudd a defender of Americanism. Rugg and Columbia Teachers College associates. Rugg claims John D. Rockefeller, Jr. sponsorship through Lincoln School affiliation. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. asks Abraham Flexner for clarification. Rugg not financed by Rockefellers. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    61.3
  - Democracy - Citizenship Educational Service, 1940-1942 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    Interdenominational group supporting democracy. Issued pamphlets against 5th Column. No Rockefeller interest. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    61.4
  - Democracy - Race Relations - Minorities, 1943-1961 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    Plans and programs for the hiring relations presented to the Rockefellers. Winthrop Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller take forthright position. Negro, Jew are center of attention. Descriptions of betterment work by civil rights groups. Appeals for aid or interest usually declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Winthrop Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, David Freeman, Warren Lindquist.
    61.5
  - Democracy - Race Relations - Minorities, 1943-1961 (Box 9, Folder 0047A)
  - Democracy - Fair Employment Practices Commission and Act, 1945-1950 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    Clippings reporting progress of programs. New York and Washington D.C. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. attitude in radio speech. Nelson A. Rockefeller made single contribution to National Committee supporting Federal legislation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Frank Jamieson.
    61.6
  - Democracy - Common Council for American Unity, 1941-1961 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    Merged with American Federation of International Institute to become American Council for Nationalities Service. To improve understanding between groups of Americans. Improve lot of immigrants. Encourage naturalization. Rockefeller Brothers Fund sent contributions. No interest shown by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Letters from Americans Campaign. Winthrop Rockefeller gifts, 1948-1953, $56,000. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Winthrop Rockefeller.
    61.7
    See also Series P - Welfare, General Interests, Boxes 29-30, Folders 312-320.
  - Democracy - Common Council for American Unity, 1941-1961 (Box 9, Folder 0049A)
  - Democracy - Friends of Democracy, 1939-1949 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    Created to arouse Americans to uphold the constitution and protect Democracy. Pointed out the evil of the Gestapo. After war kept on guard against native Fascists. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    61.8
  - Democracy - Freedom House, 1942-1961 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    Origins with WWII. Dorothy Thompson and Herbert Agar were leaders. After war fight against Communism. One gift, Nelson A. Rockefeller. Activities. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Dorothy Thompson, Herbert Agar, Wendell Willkie, Archibald MacLeish.
    61.9
  - Democracy - Southern Regional Council, Inc., 1946-1960 (Box 10, Folder 52)
    Formerly Commission on Interracial Cooperation. Bi-racial group to promote equality of opportunity in the South. Printed material. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Winthrop Rockefeller, George S. Mitchell, Harold C. Fleming.
    61.10
  - Democracy - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc., 1943-1954 (Box 10, Folder 53)
    No Rockefeller interest. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. refused to address meeting. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Corliss Lamont.
    61.11
  - Democracy - Common Cause, Inc., 1947-1951 (Box 10, Folder 54)
    Defense of the American ideal. Sent packages to Europe's needy. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined contribution. Cause mostly anti-leftist. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
    61.12
  - Democracy - Advertising Council, 1946-1961 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd made stock gift toward Americanism Campaign in 1952. Declined attending functions. Round Table project, John D. Rockefeller 3rd sponsorship. "What is America" by Arthur Goodfriend is result. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, E. B. Young, Sherman Adams, T. S. Repplier.
    61.13
  - Democracy - American Committee for Cultural Freedom, 1951-1957 (Box 10, Folder 56)
    Designed to combat Communist propaganda and aid refugee intellectuals. Office interested in organizations, but did not participate. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, E. B. Young.
    61.14
  - Democracy - American Committee for Cultural Freedom, 1951-1957 (Box 10, Folder 0056A)
  - Democracy - Committee for Free Asia, 1951-1961 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    Name changed to Asia Foundation. Provide program to develop democratic institutions in Asia. The Asia Foundation, by-laws, John D. Rockefeller 3rd declines Board membership. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Robert Blum, Lynam Hoover.
    61.15
  - Democracy - Fund for the Republic, 1953-1961 (Box 11, Folder 58)
    Newspaper accounts of controversies over Fund. Some reports by the Fund. No office participation in work of the Fund.
    61.16
  - Democracy - Civil Rights Committee, Inc., 1947-1959 (Box 11, Folder 59)
    Information on civil rights organizations. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard.
    61.21
  - Democracy - Civil Rights Committee, Inc., 1951-1959 (Box 11, Folder 0059A)
  - Democracy - American Economic Foundation, 1946-1960 (Box 11, Folder 60)
    Described as more or less "middle of the road" organization trying to promote a particular point of view in schools and colleges. Appeals declined. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    61.22
- Fire Companies
  - Fire Companies - Tarrytown Fire Companies - General, 1911-1952 (Box 11, Folder 61)
    Rockefeller contributions to and relations with independent and volunteer fire companies in the area. Personal interest in Pocantico Hills Company. Development of fixed policy of giving to several fire companies. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. handles contributions for family. Some special contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, H. J. Nelson, Arthur W. Packard.
    174
  - Fire Companies - Tarrytown Fire Companies - General, 1929-1961 (Box 11, Folder 62)
  - Fire Companies - Tarrytown Fire Companies - Archville Fire Department, 1930-1961 (Box 11, Folder 63)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's contributions.
  - Fire Companies - Tarrytown Fire Companies - Rescue Hose Company, 1910-1951 (Box 12, Folder 64)
  - Fire Companies - Tarrytown Fire Companies - Union Hose Company, 1915-1939 (Box 12, Folder 65)
  - Fire Companies - New York Fire Department, 1920-1961 (Box 12, Folder 66)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made $100 annual contributions to Fire Department Honor Emergency Fund after 1947 instead of buying tickets. Discontinued in 1952. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    174.1
  - Fire Companies - Miscellaneous Fire Companies, 1953-1959 (Box 12, Folder 67)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. $25 gifts to Croton village fire department. Sleepy Hollow Restorations assumed responsibility for gift after 1959. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel.
    174.2
  - Fire Companies - Hilltop Engine Company #1, 1927-1960 (Box 12, Folder 68)
    Purchase of service flag. Invitations to dinner declined. Gift of $1,000 for twenty-fifth anniversary-celebration. Other gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard.
    174H
  - Fire Companies - Hilltop Engine Company #1 - New Equipment, 1936-1937 (Box 12, Folder 69)
    Purchase of fire truck. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest.
  - Fire Companies - Pocantico Hook and Ladder Company, 1948-1958 (Box 12, Folder 70)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions.
- Grand Army of the Republic
  - Grand Army of the Republic - Memorial Day, 1920-1955 (Box 12, Folder 71)
    Requests for donations. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made annual contributions of $100 and a few small extra gifts. He consistently refused to serve on committees. Contributions were made until 1930 when they were discontinued by a vote of the Benevolence Committee. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson.
    7
- Highways
  - Highways - National Highways Protective Society, 1909-1922 (Box 12, Folder 72)
    Investigated evils created by automobiles. Built playgrounds, gardens to keep children off the streets. John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed nominal amounts each year. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
    15
  - Highways - Roadside Development - Billboards, 1937-1953 (Box 12, Folder 73)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's interest in beautifying roadsides. Campaigns in Virginia, New York. Since oil companies were the most obvious offenders, the Rockefellers were frequently called on for action. Laurance S. Rockefeller leads in legislative contest in New York. Shows family's interest in pure beauty. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Robert Moses.
  - Highways - Roadside Development - Billboards, 1937-1953 (Box 12, Folder 0073A)
  - Highways - Roadside Development - Billboards - Todd-Stagg Bill, 1938-1939 (Box 12, Folder 74)
    Legislative contest to regulate billboards in New York state. Abby Aldrich Rockefeller underwrote pamphlets against billboards. No results shown in file. Correspondents include Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Robert Moses, Jay Downer.
- Juries
  - Juries - Grand Jury, 1911-1955 (Box 13, Folder 75)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Nelson A. Rockefeller service on Grand Juries. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    8
  - Juries - Grand Jury - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, 1936-1941 (Box 13, Folder 76)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd not called to serve.
  - Juries - Grand Jury - Federal Grand Jury Association, 1938-1960 (Box 13, Folder 77)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller a life member. Not active.
  - Juries - Sheriffs Jury, 1918-1946 (Box 13, Folder 78)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. appointed member of 3rd panel, 1920; makes an issue over liquor served at banquet, 1924. Attended panel sessions frequently. Served until he reached retirement age. Questionable value of service of Sheriff's Jury to city. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Sheriffs of New York County.
    8.1
  - Juries - New York State Sheriff Association, 1936-1950 (Box 13, Folder 79)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes to fund of association for welfare of deputy sheriffs. Contributed in name of family members living in Westchester. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    8.2
  - Juries - Grand Jury Association of New York County, 1914-1961 (Box 13, Folder 80)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s nominal membership in organization, 1917-1925. Sporadic attempts to get a contribution were unsuccessful. Supported investigation of Grand Jury list. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    8.3
  - Juries - Grand Jury Association of New York County - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1935-1961 (Box 13, Folder 81)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd was a member of Association. Made small contributions over dues. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Juries - Grand Jury Association of New York County - David Rockefeller, 1935-1961 (Box 13, Folder 0081A)
    David Rockefeller was a member of Association. Made small contributions over dues. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
- League of Women Voters
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S., Inc., 1922-1952 (Box 13, Folder 82)
    Formerly National League of Women Voters. Organized in 1920 to prepare women for the responsibilities of voting. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made annual contributions on advice of Raymond B. Fosdick. Program and policies. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    148
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S., Inc. - Contributions, 1943-1949 (Box 13, Folder 83)
    Formerly National League of Women Voters. Contributions made by Nelson A. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S., Inc. - Contributions, 1943-1949 (Box 13, Folder 0083A)
    Formerly National League of Women Voters. Contributions made by David Rockefeller.
  - League of Women Voters, New York City, 1921-1961 (Box 14, Folder 84)
    Formerly New York League of Women Voters. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to annual needs of League. Also by David Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. Goals, methods of League. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., David Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard.
    148.1
  - League of Women Voters, New York City - Contributions, 1937-1961 (Box 14, Folder 85)
    Formerly New York League of Women Voters. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest, list of contributions. Nelson A. Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller contributions. Special gifts made.
  - League of Women Voters, New York City - Contributions, 1937-1961 (Box 14, Folder 0085A)
    Formerly New York League of Women Voters. David Rockefeller contributions.
  - League of Women Voters, New York City - David Rockefeller, 1947-1961 (Box 14, Folder 86)
    Formerly New York League of Women Voters. David Rockefeller contributes to booklet of quotes. David Rockefeller invited to be speaker for luncheon, declined. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel, Mrs. Zelia Ruebhausen.
  - League of Women Voters, New York City - David Rockefeller Contributions, 1946-1961 (Box 14, Folder 87)
    Formerly New York League of Women Voters. David Rockefeller's annual contributions. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Mrs. Zelia Ruebhausen, Mrs. Charles E. Heming, Arthur W. Packard, Rita H. Morris.
  - League of Women Voters of Tarrytown, 1950-1961 (Box 14, Folder 88)
    Annual contributions by David Rockefeller. Correspondents include David Rockefeller, Dana S. Creel.
    148.2
  - Westchester League of Women Voters, 1940-1958 (Box 15, Folder 89)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller made $100 annual contributions.
    148.3
  - Westchester League of Women Voters, 1940-1958 (Box 15, Folder 0089A)
    David Rockefeller made $100 annual contributions.
- Mayor's Committee
  - Mayor's Committee, 1949-1954 (Box 15, Folder 90)
    Invitations to dinners, requests for contributions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Edmond A. Guggenheim, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    17
  - Mayor's Committee - I Am an American Day, Mobilization Day, 1941-1946 (Box 15, Folder 91)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. member of committees. Contribution by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and sons.
  - Mayor's Committee - I Am an American Day, Mobilization Day, 1941-1946 (Box 15, Folder 0091A)
  - Mayor's Committee - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1910-1917 (Box 15, Folder 92)
    17.2
  - Mayor's Committee - Unemployment - Credit Unions, 1914-1915 (Box 15, Folder 93)
    17.1
- New York City and New York State
  - New York City and New York State - Department of Parks - Central Park and Others, 1914-1960 (Box 15, Folder 94)
    John Jay Park lighting; Park south of International House. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to $26,500 for grading latter. Hoffman Island. Damrosh Memorial contribution. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, W. W. Bosworth, Cabot Ward, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Robert Moses, Jay Downer.
    66
  - New York City and New York State - Department of Parks - Junior Protective League, New York City Parks, 1935-1937 (Box 15, Folder 95)
    Organization of children to protect New York City parks.
  - New York City and New York State - Department of Parks - Battery Park Improvements, 1940-1957 (Box 15, Folder 96)
    Appeal for interest, declined.
  - New York City and New York State - Mayors Advisory Committee, 1954-1957 (Box 15, Folder 97)
    Report on economy, Program on Handling of City-owned Real Estate. Correspondents include Nathan Straus, W. Lindquist.
    66.1
  - New York City and New York State - Mayor's Advisory Committee, 1954-1957 (Box 15, Folder 0097A)
    Raymond S. Rubinon asks David Rockefeller's support for Executive Director's position. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State - Mayors Advisory Committee - Committee on Electronic Business Machines, 1954-1955 (Box 15, Folder 98)
    Report made by special committee. David Rockefeller, chairman, Robert Dowling.
  - New York City and New York State, 1940-1950 (Box 16, Folder 99)
    A file showing the city's problems. Promotional civic activities: trade fairs, aid to City departments, transit fare, traffic relief, city parks, bridges. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions. Requests to Messrs. Rockefeller to serve on committees, declined. Plans and programs. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributed $5,000 to city planning conference at Hofstra College in 1955. Summer festivals. Correspondents include Robert Moses, W. T. Lindquist, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    66.2
    See also Mayors Committee files in Box 15.
  - New York City and New York State, 1940-1950 (Box 16, Folder 0099A)
    David Rockefeller contributed $5,000 to city planning conference at Hofstra College in 1955. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State, 1947-1954 (Box 16, Folder 100)
  - New York City and New York State, 1947-1954 (Box 16, Folder 0100A)
  - New York City and New York State, 1954-1959 (Box 16, Folder 101)
    A file showing the city's problems. Promotional civic activities: trade fairs, aid to City departments, transit fare, traffic relief, city parks, bridges. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions. Requests to Messrs. Rockefeller to serve on committees, declined. Plans and programs. David Rockefeller and Laurance S. Rockefeller contribute $5,000 to city planning conference at Hofstra College in 1955. Summer festivals. Correspondents include Robert Moses, W. T. Lindquist, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State, 1956-1959 (Box 16, Folder 102)
  - New York City and New York State, 1956-1959 (Box 16, Folder 0102A)
  - New York City and New York State, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 103)
    A file showing the city's problems. Promotional civic activities: trade fairs, aid to City departments, transit fare, traffic relief, city parks, bridges. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions. Requests to Messrs. Rockefeller to serve on committees, declined. Plans and programs. Summer festivals. Harold Wilm elected commissioner, New York State Conservation Department. Correspondents include Robert Moses, W. T. Lindquist, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State, 1960-1961 (Box 17, Folder 104)
    A file showing the city's problems. Promotional civic activities: trade fairs, aid to City departments, transit fare, traffic relief, city parks, bridges. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s opinions. Requests to Messrs. Rockefeller to serve on committees, declined. Plans and programs. Summer festivals. Correspondents include Robert Moses, W. T. Lindquist, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - New York City and New York State, 1960-1961 (Box 17, Folder 104A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material.
  - New York City and New York State - 300th Anniversary Celebration, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 105)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributes to celebration expenses.
  - New York City and New York State - 300th Anniversary Celebration, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 0105A)
    David Rockefeller contributes to celebration expenses.
  - New York City and New York State - Civil Service Awards, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 106)
    Planned organization to improve city employees. Nothing developed from it.
  - New York City and New York State - Metropolitan Association of the Amateur Athletic Union of the United States, 1953-1961 (Box 17, Folder 107)
    Requests to act as sponsors of dinners mostly declined. David Rockefeller acted for dinner for Robert Moses in 1953.
  - New York City and New York State - Golden Jubilee Celebration, 1948, 1947-1950 (Box 17, Folder 108)